Guide to the Henry R. Luce Papers 1894-2004 (bulk, 1932-1967) MS 3014
New-York Historical Society
- Series III. Notable Memoranda, 1931-1967; 2.6 Linear feet
  - Memoranda, 1954 (Box 56, Folder 7)
    Includes promotional broadsides announcing the creation of SPORTS ILLUSTRATED and a summary of HRL's off-the-cuff talk to explain the genesis of the new magazine and his personal feelings about sport. Also includes the memoranda "The State of The Magazine (and Time Inc.)," "A Balanced View of the Italian Situation," and "The Economic Situation in Italy." In addition there is a carbon copy of a letter from HRL to Aga Khan regarding his manuscript, and copies of correspondence with Winston Churchill.
  - Memoranda (folder 1 of 3), 1955 (Box 57, Folder 1)
    Includes memos regarding LIFE "Concrete Suggestions" and "LIFE- The 1955 Model," test mailings, circulation and formula for SPORTS ILLUSTRATED, and the policy on China. In addition there is a copy of a letter to Earl Warren.
  - Memoranda (folder 2 of 3), 1955 (Box 57, Folder 2)
    Includes memoranda dealing with a "reconsideration" of FORTUNE, its formula. and its editorial plans for 1955 and 1956. Also includes text of letter sent to King of Saudi Arabia Su'ud ibn 'Abd al Aziz al Su'ud and a draft of HRL's article "The Purpose of Life on Earth" as it will be conceived of in 1980 and related correspondence.
  - Memoranda (folder 3 of 3), 1955 (Box 57, Folder 3)
    Includes a carbon copy letter to Leo Burnett dealing with the meaning and purpose of SPORTS ILLUSTRATED and the memo "LIFE - The 1955 Model."
  - Memoranda - SPORTS ILLUSTRATED Prospectus, 1955 (Box 57, Folder 4)
    Includes drafts of "A Prospectus for American Magazine About Sports," "The Formula for SPORTS ILLUSTRATED" and an annotated original draft of the SPORTS ILLUSTRATED prospectus under the working name "Spectacle." Also includes the letter sent to Leo Burnett regarding the meaning and purpose of SPORTS ILLUSTRATED in booklet form.
  - Memoranda (folder 1 of 2), 1956 (Box 57, Folder 5)
    Includes memoranda dealing with the fallout over the LIFE article "How Dulles Averted War," HRL's thoughts after serving as Acting Managing Editor of TIME, and the recall of an entire issue of FORTUNE due to an article with implications for national security of the U.S. Additional memoranda address the future of ARCHITECTURAL FORUM and the revisions of the SPORTS ILLUSTRATED formula and make-up.
  - Memoranda (folder 2 of 2), 1956 (Box 57, Folder 6)
    Includes memoranda regarding the reorientation of LIFE International editorial program, cigarettes and cancer, and "What Price LIFE?" regarding the increase of the magazine's price. Also contains HRL's summary of his lunch conversation topics with Louis Jones.
  - Memoranda, 1957 (Box 57, Folder 7)
    Includes memoranda regarding investments in Eastex Mill, Time Inc. budget policy, Earl Warren, Brennan and the Supreme Court, and the proposal for running "The Changing American People" series in LIFE.
  - Memoranda (folder 1 of 2), 1958 (Box 57, Folder 8)
    Includes a "Perspective" concerning each of Time Inc.'s magazines, and a set of memoranda regarding LIFE's editorial operations "Speaking of LIFE: Where Are We and Where Do We Go From Here?"
  - Memoranda (folder 2 of 2), 1958 (Box 58, Folder 1)
    Includes memoranda giving HRL's views of the recession and depression, summary of efforts to make LIFE a better magazine, and a meeting with John Foster Dulles. There is also memoranda regarding SPORTS ILLUSTRATED "The Stage We've Reached" and the "Ten-Point Program to Keep on Achieving Greatness in Popular Journalism" for LIFE. In addition there are carbon copies of letters to Mr. and Mrs. Dwight D. Eisenhower and Norman Cousins.
  - Memoranda, 1959 (Box 58, Folder 2)
    Includes an untitled speech regarding business corporations and freedom, "A Note on the Total Editorial Job" regarding the job of the top editors of Time Inc. magazines, and "The Aims of a Free People" speech by John W. Gardner in pamphlet form with HRL's analysis. Also includes memoranda dealing with Time Inc. policy on speech-writing for political candidates, national purpose, and a draft of TIME reprospectus "TIME Tomorrow." In addition there is a carbon copy of a letter to Chief Justice Warren, and the foreword and notes for Max Way's book.
  - Memoranda (folder 1 of 2), 1960 (Box 58, Folder 3)
    Includes memoranda dealing with civil rights, America's national purpose, the reformulation of the SPORTS ILLUSTRATED prospectus, and HRL's reports on his impressions of India, Japan, and Taiwan from his 1960 world trip. Also includes memos from Dick Clurman to HRL "What TIME-LIFE Correspondents Do--and Should Do" and from John Boyle "The Function of the Correspondent," with additional memos titled "Notes for a Philosophy of Sports" and "Some Thoughts on FORTUNE in its Present Stage or An Approach to the FORTUNE Problem - Whatever It Is." There are also carbon copies of letters to and from President Eisenhower and carbon copies of a letter and response to Thomas M. Cleland on the 30th anniversary of FORTUNE.
  - Memoranda (folder 2 of 2), 1960 (Box 58, Folder 4)
    Contains mostly memoranda regarding LIFE including "Further Notes on LIFE is for Nixon," "A Note of LIFE in the Sixties," "Thoughts on TIME and LIFE and the 1960 Campaign," "A Note on LIFE in 1939," "The Meaning of LIFE," and "LIFE - A New Prospectus for the Sixties."
  - Memoranda (folder 1 of 2), 1961 (Box 58, Folder 5)
    Includes memoranda listing subjects for major LIFE articles, HRL's views on the Kennedy State of the Union Speech, "Work Program for LIFE," and "Henry R. Luce Visit With President John F. Kennedy - July 31, 1961." In addition there are copies of letters sent to and received from John F. Kennedy, copies of correspondence responding to a complaint from King Hussein of Jordan, and the C.J.V. Murphy article on the failed Cuban invasion in FORTUNE.
  - Memoranda (folder 2 of 2), 1961 (Box 58, Folder 6)
    Includes a partial transcript of HRL's press conference, and a memo on Henry Pomeroy Davison, the first person to invest in Time Inc. In addition there are carbon copies of letters to Willy Brandt, Viggo Kampmann, and Hassen Ebtehaj.
  - Memoranda (folder 1 of 2), 1962 (Box 58, Folder 7)
    Includes memoranda regarding the merging of Time Inc. domestic and foreign news services, an outline on a series of articles on Greece, and a special travel issue of LIFE. In addition there are carbon copies of letters to John F. Kennedy, David Brinkley, Eisenhower, and to Adnoldo Mondadori regarding the publication of Panorama.
  - Memoranda (folder 2 of 2), 1962 (Box 59, Folder 1)
    Includes memoranda regarding LIFE's present state and near-term future, profitability of Time Inc., and a proposal for a supplement to LIFE on science. In addition there are copies of letters to John F. Kennedy and Hubert H. Humphrey.
  - Memoranda, 1963 (Box 59, Folder 2)
    Includes memoranda regarding a retrospectus for FORTUNE and LIFE, and a prospectus for a law section in TIME titled "TIME's Missing Section." In addition there are carbon copies of letters to Winston Churchill, Dwight D. Eisenhower, Douglas MacArthur, Madame Chiang Kai-shek, and a thermofax copy of a telegram to Jacqueline Kennedy following the John F. Kennedy assassination.
  - Memoranda, 1964 (Box 59, Folder 3)
    Includes a copy of Louis Banks's notes on a talk with HRL, memoranda regarding HRL's conversations with President Johnson, the announcement of HRL's resignation as Editor-in-Chief, and significant stories from the Republican Presidential Convention.
  - Memoranda, 1965 (Box 59, Folder 4)
    Includes copy of a memorandum regarding FORTUNE's departments, and a copy of letter to William O. Douglas.
  - Memoranda, 1966 (Box 59, Folder 5)
    Includes a copy of memo from Tom Griffith to Hedley Donovan "Domestic Issues," guidelines for Time Inc., and copy of memo regarding the Republican nominee for the 1968 presidential election. Also includes a copy of letter to Hubert H. Humphrey and a copy of the transcript "Fulbright Discusses TIME and LIFE" from the WCBS-TV program Vietnam Perspective: China and the War.
  - Memoranda, 1967 (Box 59, Folder 6)
    Includes copies of letters to and response from Robert F. Kennedy, handwritten and typed "Notes on the Newspaper Question," and a signed original letter from Major General Neil D. Van Sickle following HRL's death.
  - Selected Documents by HRL, 1961-1967 (Box 167, Folder 5)
    Includes carbon and photocopies of memoranda, correspondence, clippings, and speech factsheets dealing with editorial and management issues, the global situation, and HRL's thoughts. Also includes copies of correspondence with John F. Kennedy and a carbon copy memo describing HRL's meeting with John F. Kennedy on 24 October 1962.
- Series IV. Family Correspondence and School Records, 1898-1973 (bulk, 1898-1948); 8.2 Linear feet
  The series is arranged mostly chronologically with the files divided into prominent periods of HRL's life consisting of his time as a child in China (1898-1907); his trip to the United States (1906-1907); family vacation at Iltus Huk, China (1908); Chefoo School (1908-1912); journey from China to attend school in St. Albans, England and his subsequent travels around Europe (1912-1913); Hotchkiss School (1913-1916); the summer he spent working for the newspaper the Springfield Republican prior to his entry into Yale (1916); his time at Yale (1916-1920), with a break for summer vacation when HRL worked on a farm (1917), and his military service at Camp Jackson, South Carolina and Camp Taylor, Kentucky (1918); studies at Oxford and travels around Europe (1920-1921); and working in Chicago and Baltimore before leaving for New York with Briton Hadden to work on the creation of TIME (1921-1922).
  Series consists of original correspondence from Henry R. Luce (hereafter HRL) sent to his father, mother, jointly to his parents, sisters Elisabeth ("Beth"), Emmavail ("Vail") and to his brother Sheldon. In addition to the correspondence there are original poems, stories, sermons, doodles, stamps, as well as exams, essays, report cards and other school ephemera from his time in Chefoo, Hotchkiss, and Yale. Some of HRL's correspondence contains notes added by his parents and by others. A transcription manuscript of the original correspondence, which was part of a project undertaken in 1972-1973, is available within the series. There are also multiple sets of Photostatic positives and negatives at the end of the series. Originals, transcriptions and Photostats have not been fully reconciled. A small amount of correspondence in the series was not written by HRL and is indicated where found.
  Additional correspondence and other materials related to HRL's family members are located in series III, subseries A, filed under individual names of the Luce family.
  - Original Letters (Box -, Folder -)
  - Letters from the Beginning, 1898-1907, circa 1898-1907 (Box 71, Folder 6)
    Includes a set of pages from what appears to be a baby album containing the announcement of HRL's birth, his weight and the bestowal of his name; handwritten notes about HRL, a sketch of a house plan, letters to his father and to Dr. Kingdom which were dictated to his mother and signed by HRL, drawing of a flag and shapes, arithmetic and grammar test with a grade, a blank Chefoo school form, a report card from Chefoo Preparatory School, handwritten prayers, poems, the sermon "The Story of David," a short story "A Story of a Cat and Dog," drawing of two trees, apology note to his mother, and two valentine cards made by HRL for his father and mother.
  - Letters, 1906-1907 (folder 1 of 2), circa 1906-1907 (Box 71, Folder 7)
    Includes a letter sent from Pelham Manor, NY with a drawing of a steamship, sermons, Sunday school lessons written on the back of a large calendar page, letter to HRL's mother Elizabeth Luce from her Aunt Clara, and a letter of gratitude from Uncle Charlie in Scranton, PA.
  - Letters, 1906-1907 (folder 2 of 2), circa 1906-1907 (Box 71, Folder 8)
    Includes a drawing, notes on a sermon, and a plan to start a poultry farm.
  - Iltus Huk and Chefoo, 1908 (folder 1 of 2), circa 1908 (Box 71, Folder 9)
    Includes a sketch of a house plan, and the compositions written by HRL "Work, Bless, Preach and Pray: A Missionary Hymn by Henry Robinson Luce written in 1908" and "Jesu Domminus." Pages from two of the letters are missing.
  - Iltus Huk and Chefoo, 1908 (folder 2 of 2), circa 1908 (Box 72, Folder 1)
    Contains a letter to Dr. Vail together with a large number of stamps in envelopes labeled 1.China (3 stamps); 2. Hong Kong (5 stamps); 3.China?-Kewriang (1 stamp); 4. Japan (6 stamps); 5.China?-Kiautschou (4 stamps); 6.China Deutsches Reich (1 stamp); 7.China - Shanghai (1 stamp); 8. China (7 stamps). Additional stamps in unnumbered envelopes consist of China - Hankow, Chefoo (2 stamps); Great Britain (4 stamps); Japan (3 stamps); Italy (1 stamp); Bavaria (1 stamp); Austria (4 stamps); Argentina (1 stamp); United States (1 stamp); Cape of Good Hope (1 stamp); Australia - Western Australia, New South Wales (3 stamps); Egypt (2 stamps); Netherlands (5 stamps); Siam (2 stamps); Belgium (2 stamps); Denmark (1 stamp); France (1 stamp); Sweden (1 stamp); Switzerland (1 stamp); Portugal (1 stamp); and Miscellaneous (6 stamps).
  - Chefoo, 1909 (Box 72, Folder 2)
    Pages of some of the letters are missing.
  - Chefoo, 1910 (Box 72, Folder 3)
    Includes letters with stories "How the Crow Got It's Streak White" and "How the Man Became Master." One of the letters includes a set of pictographic riddles on well known books.
  - Chefoo, 1911 (Box 72, Folder 4)
    Includes HRL's letters from Peking, Tientsin and Tsing Tau. One of the letters includes an outline of work HRL has to do in school. Two of the letters discuss the Chinese Revolution.
  - Chefoo, 1912 (folder 1 of 2) (Box 72, Folder 5)
    Includes an extract from HRL's letter to Mrs. Linen written in Mrs. Luce's hand, a handwritten notice announcing a debate where HRL will preside as chairman and his opening statement at the debate, the essay "The Use and Abuse of Fiction," a letter dated 24 March 1912 discussing a plan to start a school newspaper with HRL as Editor- in-Chief, and a letter from HRL to Miss Dolph.
  - Chefoo, 1912 (folder 2 of 2) (Box 72, Folder 6)
    Includes the poem "Longing" written by HRL on the day before his 14th birthday, the poem "To a Missionary," and letter sent from Tengchow and Iltus Huk.
  - Trip to Suez, England, Europe, USA to Hotchkiss (folder 1 of 3), 1912-1913 (Box 72, Folder 7)
    Contains letters sent from Tientsin Puko Railroad, Nanking, Shanghai, Penang, Malaysia, ship Prinz Eitel Friedrich; Hong Kong, Singapore, Ceylon (Sri Lanka), Port Said, Egypt, Naples and Genoa, Italy. Includes a passport photograph of HRL, a letter from Ella R. Shields to Mrs. Luce regarding HRL, a letter sent from Sri Lanka with two tree leaves taped to the front page. Pages of some of the letters are missing.
  - Trip to Suez, England, Europe, USA to Hotchkiss (folder 2 of 3), 1912-1913 (Box 72, Folder 8)
    Contains correspondence sent from St. Albans, England, France, Switzerland, Italy, Germany, and aboard the Hamburg-Amerika Line ship "Patricia." Includes HRL's poem "Idolatry." Part of one of the letters is missing.
  - Trip to Suez, England, Europe, USA to Hotchkiss, 1912-1913 (folder 3 of 3) - oversize (Box OS-Medium)
    Contains a map, likely of Brussels with HRL's text on the back describing his trip to Germany and Belgium.
  - Hotchkiss and Yale Orations, Speeches, etc. 1913-1920, 1913-1920, 1946 (Box 72, Folder 10)
    Includes the Van Dyck prize oration "Through Precedent to Liberty," the "Tentative 1916 Class Poem," "Kenneth Grahame," an untitled essay in competition for a prize, oration on the armament of the United States, the play "The Fortunes of War," the poem "Herod: Thus Spake Herod the Great," speech given before the Forum Literary Society titled "The Causes of the European War," the oration "Patches of Light," clipping of HRL's "Class Poem -1920," a Hotchkiss School Class Day Exercises Program; HRL's poem "Hotchkiss, Thy Blue and White!," and the oration "Individualism and Conviction." Also includes correspondence regarding HRL's address at Duke University in March of 1946.
  - Hotchkiss and Yale Poems 1913-1920, circa 1908-1920 (Box 73, Folder 1)
    Some of the poems were written by HRL before attending Hotchkiss and Yale. Poems include "August the Twenty Nine," "Life," "A Salvation Army Hymn," "Reflections on 'Twenty-Fourth of September,'" "Consecration," "Hotchkiss Thy Blue and White!," "La Fin," "Immortality," "To China," "Stanzas," "Shadows," "In Heaven," "Sacrifice," "God in the Eventide!," "Reveille!," and a handwritten version of "Class Poem - 1920."
  - Hotchkiss and Yale - Tests and Examinations (folder 1 of 2), 1913-1920, 1960 (Box 73, Folder 2)
    Includes a letter from Professor Edgar Eugene Robinson sending HRL his Yale thesis "Theodore Roosevelt," and various blue book exams.
  - Hotchkiss and Yale - Tests and Examinations (folder 2 of 2), 1913-1920 (Box 73, Folder 3)
    Includes HRL's Greek exams, and a blue book with the highest mark ever given at the time on a final exam in English, and a December 1915 issue of The Hotchkiss Literary Monthly where HRL served as editor.
  - Hotchkiss, 1913 (Box 72, Folder 9)
    Includes two of HRL's graded school papers "One of My Public Projects" and "A Lesson Taught Me by Franklin," a letter from HRL describing arrival in the United States and his preparations to go to school, and a clipping from a Hotchkiss publication mentioning HRL.
  - Hotchkiss, 1914 (folder 1 of 2) (Box 73, Folder 4)
    Includes a detailed chart of miles walked by HRL, members of his family, and others, an untitled Christmas poem, and a letter sent from Chicago.
  - Hotchkiss, 1914 (folder 2 of 2), 1913-1915 (Box 73, Folder 5)
    Includes clippings from The Hotchkiss Record, a note added to one of HRL's letters by his mother to his father, letter to HRL from his father, notes on humility and forgiveness, a program for the Agora vs. Forum annual debate, a physical training department card with HRL's data, report cards, a prayer meeting card, honor roll cards, a ticket to the football game between Harvard and Yale, a ticket for the literary contest between Agora and Forum societies, and correspondence sent to HRL as editor of The Hotchkiss Record and The Hotchkiss Literary Monthly.
  - Hotchkiss, 1915 (folder 1 of 2) (Box 73, Folder 6)
    Includes the words for a school song by HRL "The White and Blue."
  - Hotchkiss, 1915 (folder 2 of 2) (Box 73, Folder 7)
    Includes letters sent by HRL from Mill Valley, California, the West Coast and Chicago during his summer vacation.
  - Hotchkiss, 1916 (Box 73, Folder 8)
    Includes the first typewritten letter sent by HRL to his parents, a letter from Knox Hat Company to HRL regarding advertisement in The Hotchkiss Literary Monthly, and a letter from H. G. Buehler, headmaster of Hotchkiss, to Henry W. Luce complaining about HRL.
  - Summer of 1916 at Springfield, before Yale (Box 74, Folder 1)
    Includes a note to HRL from his father regarding Dr. Buehler, a letter regarding journalistic opportunities in China, and letters from Linair and Williams Club in NY. Part of a letter is missing.
  - Yale, 1916-1917 (folder 1 of 2) (Box 74, Folder 2)
    Includes two typed letters to HRL from his father, HRL letters sent from NY and Chicago, and HRL's report card.
  - Yale, 1916-1917 (folder 2 of 2) (Box 74, Folder 3)
    Includes a typed letter to HRL from his father giving his son advice on classes, fraternities and other matters pertaining to Yale.
  - Summer of 1917 (folder 1 of 2) (Box 74, Folder 4)
    Letters from Linair where HRL spent the summer working on a farm.
  - Summer of 1917 (folder 2 of 2) (Box 74, Folder 5)
  - Yale, 1917-1918 (folder 1 of 2) (Box 74, Folder 6)
    Includes an Alpha Delta Phi fraternity card addressed to HRL and the poem "Le Credo Patriotique" by Henry Lavedan.
  - Yale, 1917-1918 (folder 2 of 2) (Box 74, Folder 7)
    6 May 1918 letter includes HRL's opinions of marriage.
  - Yale Daily News (Special File), 1918, 1917-1918 (Box 74, Folder 8)
    Includes clipping announcing HRL's election to the editorial board of the News, a note on a telegram form from HRL's father? regarding HRL having been elected, and other correspondence regarding HRL's chairmanship of the News.
  - Wartime Letters from the Summer of 1918 to January 1919 and Return to Yale (Box 75, Folder 1)
    Includes HRL's military pass, transparencies of some of the letters, a letter to Aunt Flo, a letter to Mrs. McCormick, a letter to HRL from Dean of Yale, Frederick S. Jones, and a sketch of Camp Taylor? Part of a letter is missing.
  - Yale, 1919-1920 (folder 1 of 2) (Box 75, Folder 2)
  - Yale, 1919-1920 (folder 2 of 2) (Box 75, Folder 3)
    Includes an invitation to the Yale graduation ceremony and a letter sent from the Republican National Convention in Chicago.
  - Europe and Oxford, July 1920-June 23, 1921 (folder 1 of 2), 1920-1921 (Box 75, Folder 4)
    Includes a letter from Geneva, Switzerland describing HRL's experiences at the League of Nations, and a letter regarding his smoking and drinking habits.
  - Europe and Oxford, July 1920-June 23, 1921 (folder 2 of 2), 1920-1921 (Box 75, Folder 5)
    Includes letters sent from Germany, postcards of Oare Church and Lynmouth Bay, and an account of HRL's trip on the Orient Express.
  - Chicago, Baltimore and New York, 1921-1922 (Box 75, Folder 6)
    Includes correspondence regarding HRL's working on and being fired from The Chicago News, a detailed letter from HRL to his father regarding the selection of the name "TIME" for the new magazine, potential slogans, and its development and financing.
  - Letters Regarding TIME, 1925-1938 & 1947-1948 (Box 76, Folder 3)
    Includes a letter dealing with the purchase of Time Inc. stock from the Hadden estate, a clipping with a caricature of HRL at the Banff Conference, a letter dealing with prohibition of liquor advertisements, a letter to HRL's father from Corinne Thrasher with an attached memo regarding a speech HRL made at the Yale Barn affair on the degradation of civilization. Also includes a carbon copy of a letter to Winston Churchill and a letter from HRL to his mother apologizing for a TIME article on Amsterdam.
  - Unsorted Letters, 1923-1939 (folder 1 of 2) (Box 75, Folder 7)
    Includes letters mentioning a meeting with Conde Nast, wedding to Lila Luce, the birth of Henry Luce III and Peter Paul Luce, and a letter from Lila Luce to HRL's mother.
  - Unsorted Letters, 1923-1939 (folder 2 of 2) (Box 75, Folder 8)
    Includes a postcard of the Haleakala Crater in Maui, a letter sent to Kay and Reese Taylor, letters sent from HRL's first round the world trip in 1932, a letter from Lila Luce to HRL's mother with paper notes used by HRL to communicate with his wife and a nurse when he was undergoing a medical procedure, a letter discussing his appointment to have tea with Franklin D. Roosevelt, and an invitation to an exhibition and sale of items brought from England by Miss Florence T. Gay.
  - Unsorted Letters, 1940-1948 (folder 1 of 2) (Box 76, Folder 1)
  - Unsorted Letters, 1940-1948 (folder 2 of 2) (Box 76, Folder 2)
  - Transcriptions (Box -, Folder -)
  - Transcription Project Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 76, Folder 4)
  - Index and Elm Excerpts, circa 1972-1973 (Box 76, Folder 5)
  - Index for Letters from HRL Covering Pages 218-583, circa 1972-1973 (Box 76, Folder 5)
  - Transcription Manuscript (4 of 7 folders), circa 1972-1973 (Box 76, Folder 6-9)
  - Transcription Manuscript (3 of 7 folders), circa 1972-1973 (Box 77, Folder 1-3)
  - Photostats and Negatives (Box -, Folder -)